<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Time on Baruffio: a blog about Harry Potter — baruffio.com </title>
    <link>http://baruffio.com/t/time/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>A Witch or Wizard</author>
    <rights>Copyright the respective author(s); all rights reserved.</rights>
    <updated>2014-05-02 00:00:00 -0700 PDT</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#8220;It is too late, you understand me?&#8221;: Time travel in &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt;</title>
      <link>http://baruffio.com/p/time</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 00:00:00 PDT</pubDate>
      <author>[Alex Dunn]</author>
      <guid>http://baruffio.com/p/time</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here at &lt;em&gt;Baruffio&lt;/em&gt; we sometimes cast a critical eye on &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter,&lt;/em&gt;
and amuse ourselves by pointing out inconsistencies in the books (then
&lt;a href=&#34;/p/trace&#34; title=&#34;There&#39;s no Such
Thing as the Trace&#34;&gt;weaving them into conspiracy theories&lt;/a&gt;).  But time travel in &lt;em&gt;Prisoner of Azkaban&lt;/em&gt; is a
model of consistency, illustrating wonderfully how time travel
works&amp;mdash;if it&amp;rsquo;s possible at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Going back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the end of &lt;em&gt;PoA,&lt;/em&gt; Harry and Hermione wake up in the hospital
wing and learn that Sirius Black is about to receive the Dementor&amp;rsquo;s
Kiss, and that it is &lt;em&gt;too late&lt;/em&gt; to stop it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sirius has not acted like an innocent man. The attack on the Fat
Lady&amp;mdash;entering Gryffindor Tower with a knife&amp;mdash;without Pettigrew,
alive or dead, we have no chance of overturning Sirius&amp;rsquo; sentence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;But you believe us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yes, I do,&amp;rdquo; said Dumbledore quietly. &amp;ldquo;But I have no power to make
other men see the truth, or to overrule the Minister for Magic &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry stared up into the grave face and felt as though the ground
beneath him was falling sharply away.  He had grown used to the idea
that Dumbledore could solve anything.  He had expected Dumbledore to
pull some amazing solution out of the air.  But no &amp;hellip; their last
hope was gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What we need,&amp;rdquo; said Dumbledore slowly, and his light-blue eyes
moved from Harry to Hermione, &amp;ldquo;is more &lt;em&gt;time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But&amp;mdash;&amp;rdquo; Hermione began. And then her eyes became very round. &amp;ldquo;OH!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Now, pay attention,&amp;rdquo; said Dumbledore, speaking very low, and very
clearly.  &amp;ldquo;Sirius is locked in Professor Flitwick&amp;rsquo;s office on the
seventh floor.  Thirteenth window from the right of the West Tower.
If all goes well, you will be able to save more than one innocent
life tonight.  But remember this, both of you. &lt;em&gt;You must not be
seen.&lt;/em&gt; Miss Granger, you know the law&amp;mdash;you know what is at stake
&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;you&amp;mdash;must&amp;mdash;not&amp;mdash;be&amp;mdash;seen”&lt;/em&gt; (Chapter 21).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so they go back in time, to rescue Buckbeak and Sirius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;You &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be seen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s most interesting about Harry and Hermione&amp;rsquo;s journey through
time is that &lt;em&gt;they don&amp;rsquo;t actually change the past.&lt;/em&gt; When Hermione
spins the Time-Turner to send her and Harry back three hours, they&amp;rsquo;ve
already saved Buckbeak.  Rowling leaves Buckbeak&amp;rsquo;s fate deliberately
ambiguous the first time around, when Hermione, Harry, Ron, and
Scabbers leave Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s hut at sundown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rat was squealing wildly, but not loudly enough to cover up the
sounds drifting from Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s garden. There was a jumble of
indistinct male voices, a silence and then, without warning, the
unmistakeable swish and thud of an axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hermione swayed on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;They did it!&amp;rdquo; she whispered to Harry. &amp;ldquo;I d-don&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;mdash;they
did it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry&amp;rsquo;s mind had gone blank with shock. The three of them stood
transfixed with horror under the Invisibility Cloak. The very last
rays of the setting sun were casting a bloody light over the
long-shadowed grounds. Then, behind them, they heard a wild howling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hagrid,&amp;rdquo; Harry muttered. Without thinking about what he was doing,
he made to turn back, but both Ron and Hermione seized his arms
(Chapters 16&amp;ndash;17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t see Buckbeak get killed.  They don&amp;rsquo;t hear Hagrid mourning.
And for good reason, because Buckbeak &lt;em&gt;didn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; get killed, and Hagrid
isn&amp;rsquo;t howling with sorrow.  When Harry and Hermione go back in time,
the first thing they do is rescue Buckbeak from the Ministry
executioner.  While Hagrid, Dumbledore, a Ministry committee member,
and the executioner Macnair are in Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s hut, Harry unties Buckbeak
and leads him away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s back door had opened with a bang. Harry, Hermione and
Buckbeak stood quite still; even the Hippogriff seemed to be
listening intently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silence &amp;hellip; then&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Where is it?&amp;rdquo; said the reedy voice of the Committee member. &amp;ldquo;Where
is the beast?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It was tied here!&amp;rdquo; said the executioner furiously. &amp;ldquo;I saw it! Just
here!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How extraordinary,&amp;rdquo; said Dumbledore. There was a note of amusement
in his voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Beaky!&amp;rdquo; said Hagrid huskily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a swishing noise, and the thud of an axe. The executioner
seemed to have swung it into the fence in anger. And then came the
howling, and &lt;strong&gt;this time they could hear Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s words through his
sobs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Gone! Gone! Bless his little beak, he&amp;rsquo;s gone! Musta pulled himself
free! Beaky, yeh clever boy!&amp;rdquo; (Chapter 21, my emphasis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was never true that Buckbeak got executed.  Even when Harry and
Hermione are under the Invisibility Cloak with Ron and Scabbers, even
when they &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they are listening to Macnair killing the
Hippogriff, Buckbeak has already been rescued&amp;mdash;by them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the past when he casts his Patronus, either.
After he, Hermione, Ron, Sirius, Lupin, Snape, and Pettigrew leave the
Shrieking Shack, the full moon comes out and Lupin transforms into a
werewolf.  Pettigrew escapes, and everyone is scattered across the
grounds.  Harry, Hermione, and Sirius find themselves at the edge of
the Hogwarts lake, surrounded by Dementors.  Sirius and Hermione
faint, and just before Harry&amp;rsquo;s soul is sucked from his body, something
miraculous happens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something was driving the Dementors back &amp;hellip; it was circling around
him and Sirius and Hermione &amp;hellip; the rattling, sucking sounds of the
Dementors were fading. They were leaving &amp;hellip; the air was warm again
&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With every ounce of strength he could muster, Harry raised his head
a few inches and saw an animal amidst the light, galloping away
across the lake. Eyes blurred with sweat, Harry tried to make out
what it was &amp;hellip; it was bright as a unicorn.  Fighting to stay
conscious, Harry watched it canter to a halt as it reached the
opposite shore.  For a moment, Harry saw, by its brightness,
somebody welcoming it back &amp;hellip; raising his hand to pat it
&amp;hellip; someone who looked strangely familiar &amp;hellip; but it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be
&amp;hellip; (Chapter 20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first Harry thinks it&amp;rsquo;s his father who saves him, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t, and
never was.  In the next chapter, we see that he saves &lt;em&gt;himself&lt;/em&gt; from
the Dementors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry raised his head to look at the circle of Dementors across the
lake.  One of them was lowering its hood.  It was time for the
rescuer to appear&amp;mdash;but no one was coming to help this time&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it hit him&amp;mdash;he understood. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen his father&amp;mdash;he
had seen &lt;em&gt;himself&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry flung himself out from behind the bush and pulled out his
wand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;EXPECTO PATRONUM!&amp;rdquo; he yelled (Chapter 21).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Harry does this, he &lt;em&gt;isn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; changing the past.  He&amp;rsquo;s just getting
around to doing what he already did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Harry, I can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;mdash;you conjured up a Patronus that drove
away all those Dementors! That&amp;rsquo;s very, &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; advanced magic &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I knew I could do it this time,&amp;rdquo; said Harry, &amp;ldquo;because I&amp;rsquo;d already
done it &amp;hellip; Does that make sense?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything Harry and Hermione do in Chapter 21 had already occurred
when Hermione spun the Time-Turner three times.  They didn&amp;rsquo;t change
the past; everything they had to do, they had already done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why didn&amp;rsquo;t they change the past &lt;em&gt;anyway?&lt;/em&gt;  Harry tries to convince
Hermione to capture Pettigrew while he&amp;rsquo;s still in Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin with
Harry and Hermione&amp;rsquo;s past selves.  But Hermione won&amp;rsquo;t let him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hermione,&amp;rdquo; said Harry suddenly, &amp;ldquo;what if we&amp;mdash;we just run in there,
and grab Pettigrew&amp;mdash;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;No!&amp;rdquo; said Hermione in a terrified whisper. &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t you understand?
We&amp;rsquo;re breaking one of the most important wizarding laws!  Nobody&amp;rsquo;s
supposed to change time, nobody! You heard Dumbledore, if we&amp;rsquo;re
seen&amp;mdash;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;d only be seen by ourselves and Hagrid!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Harry, what do you think you&amp;rsquo;d do if you saw yourself bursting into
Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s house?&amp;rdquo; said Hermione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d&amp;mdash;I&amp;rsquo;d think I&amp;rsquo;d gone mad,&amp;rdquo; said Harry, &amp;ldquo;or I&amp;rsquo;d think there was
some Dark Magic going on&amp;mdash;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Exactly!&lt;/em&gt; You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t understand, you might even attack yourself!
Don&amp;rsquo;t you see? Professor McGonagall told me what awful things have
happened when wizards have meddled with time &amp;hellip; loads of them ended
up killing their past or future selves by mistake!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason Hermione gives as to why they don&amp;rsquo;t change the past is that
it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;dangerous.&lt;/em&gt;  She seems to believe this herself, because she
thinks she and Harry &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; changing the past, and breaking the law in
doing so.  As far as she and Harry know, Buckbeak &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; executed, and
they&amp;rsquo;re trying to change that.  Because Hermione thinks they are
changing the past, and because she thinks it&amp;rsquo;s very dangerous, she
panics whenever Harry tries to change things without thinking about
the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she needn&amp;rsquo;t have worried, because not only is changing the past
not dangerous, it&amp;rsquo;s not even &lt;em&gt;possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;The past is fixed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it impossible to change the past?  Why, for example, is it
impossible for Harry to burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin and grab Scabbers?
It&amp;rsquo;s tempting to try to explain the impossibility like this: &amp;ldquo;Harry
didn&amp;rsquo;t burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin the first time; otherwise bursting
into the cabin wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be changing that past.  But that means that
the second time around, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;too late&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;Harry already didn&amp;rsquo;t burst
into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explanation should strike you as odd; what does it mean to say
that Harry &lt;em&gt;already didn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; burst into the cabin?  Of course he hasn&amp;rsquo;t
&lt;em&gt;yet,&lt;/em&gt; but the question is whether he &lt;em&gt;will.&lt;/em&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s nothing in the
&lt;em&gt;past&lt;/em&gt; that rules out Harry bursting into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin, so why can&amp;rsquo;t
he?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an odd explanation, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s actually more or less
right.  To see why, we need to take a quick detour and introduce some
new terms for talking about time: &amp;ldquo;external time&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;personal time.&amp;rdquo;
These terms were coined by David Lewis in his 1976 paper
&lt;a href=&#34;http://kieranhealy.org/files/misc/lewis-paradoxes.pdf&#34; title=&#34;PDF&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Paradoxes of Time Travel.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; He proposes that we think about time travel as involving &amp;ldquo;a
discrepancy between time and time&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any traveler departs and then arrives at his destination; the time
elapsed from departure to arrival (positive, or perhaps zero) is the
duration of the journey.  But if he is a time traveler, the
separation in time between departure and arrival does not equal the
duration of his journey.  He departs; he travels for an hour, let us
say; then he arrives.  The time he reaches is not the time one hour
after his departure.  It is later, if he has traveled toward the
future; earlier, if he has traveled toward the past.  If he has
traveled far toward the past, it is earlier even than his
departure.  How can it be that the same two events, his departure
and his arrival, are separated by two unequal amounts of time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this riddle requires distinguishing &amp;ldquo;external time&amp;rdquo; from
&amp;ldquo;personal time.&amp;rdquo;  External time is what is recorded by clock-towers
and atomic clocks; when Harry and Hermione go back in time, they are
going back in &lt;em&gt;external time.&lt;/em&gt; But they are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going back in
&lt;em&gt;personal time.&lt;/em&gt; Personal time is what is recorded by Harry&amp;rsquo;s
wristwatch.  Lewis goes on to explain how external time and personal
time come apart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[The time traveler&amp;rsquo;s] journey takes an hour of his personal time,
let us say; his wristwatch reads an hour later at arrival than at
departure.  But the arrival is more than an hour after the departure
in external time, if he travels toward the future; or the arrival is
before the departure in external time (or less than an hour after),
if he travels toward the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Harry and Hermione&amp;rsquo;s case, the end of their journey&amp;mdash;when they
appear in the Entrance Hall&amp;mdash;is a few seconds &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the beginning
of their journey&amp;mdash;when Hermione spins the Time-Turner in the hospital
wing&amp;mdash;that is, in &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;/em&gt; time.  But the end of their journey is
three hours &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; its beginning in &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of getting at the difference between external and personal
time is this: External time is time in the third person; personal time
is time in the first person.  External time is the same for everyone;
if someone (like God) could step back and observe the universe, he
would watch it progress in external time.  Personal time is not the
same for everyone; personal time for each person corresponds&amp;mdash;more or
less&amp;mdash;to their &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt; through time.  From Harry&amp;rsquo;s perspective,
he appears in the Entrance Hall a few seconds &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Hermione spins
the Time-Turner.  He remembers being in the hospital wing immediately
prior, his watch has only moved a few seconds forward, and the
physical age of his body is a few seconds older.  (That last bit is
important: I can be confused about the progress of my own personal
time, like when I wake up and can&amp;rsquo;t remember how long I&amp;rsquo;ve slept.  But
my body has aged a certain number of hours, and I&amp;rsquo;ve moved &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; many
hours ahead in personal time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we&amp;rsquo;re talking about the life of a person, and their progress
through history, we use personal time.  Harry fainted at the edge of
the lake, surrounded by Dementors, then woke up in the hospital wing,
&lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; went back in time, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; cast the Patronus to save himself.
Those events all occurred, and they occurred &lt;em&gt;in that order&lt;/em&gt; for
Harry.  And most importantly, this is a &lt;em&gt;perfectly accurate&lt;/em&gt; way of
describing the events at the end of &lt;em&gt;Prisoner of Azkaban.&lt;/em&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s no
less accurate than a description of those events in external time.
(An external-time description would be: Harry cast the Patronus to
save himself, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; fainted at the edge of the lake, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; woke up
in the hospital wing, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; went back in time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to think of external time as &lt;em&gt;objective&lt;/em&gt; and personal time
as &lt;em&gt;subjective,&lt;/em&gt; external time as &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; and personal time as
&lt;em&gt;secondary;&lt;/em&gt; but both are equally legitimate.  Personal time isn&amp;rsquo;t
just our &lt;em&gt;opinion&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; about the passage of time.  Like I
said above, we can be unsure about how far we&amp;rsquo;ve proceeded in personal
time: if we are unconscious, we lose the ability to detect the passage
of time.  But there are other, largely objective, ways to measure how
far we move forward in personal time.  When you wake up, even if &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;
think you&amp;rsquo;ve only been asleep for a few minutes, your watch might say
otherwise, and your body will have aged as many hours as you&amp;rsquo;ve been
asleep.  You&amp;rsquo;ve progressed a certain determinate number of hours in
personal time.  And &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; fact&amp;mdash;that you&amp;rsquo;ve moved forward a number
of hours in personal time&amp;mdash;is just as &lt;em&gt;objectively true&lt;/em&gt; as the fact
that you&amp;rsquo;ve moved forward a number of hours in external time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Harry and Hermione go back in time, the &lt;em&gt;fact&lt;/em&gt; that only a few
seconds of personal time has elapsed for each of them is just as
objectively true as is the fact that they&amp;rsquo;ve moved backwards three
hours in external time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s go back to our original, tempting explanation of why it&amp;rsquo;s
impossible to change the past: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Harry didn&amp;rsquo;t burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s
cabin the first time; otherwise bursting into the cabin wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be
changing that past.  But that means that the second time around, it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt;
too late&amp;mdash;&lt;em&gt;Harry already didn&amp;rsquo;t burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; Let&amp;rsquo;s
write out that series of events in personal time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry saw Hermione find Scabbers in Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin; then left the
cabin with Ron, Hermione and Scabbers; then saw Scabbers escape and
get dragged (with Ron) into the Whomping Willow; then went into the
Shrieking Shack and out again; then fainted at the lake&amp;rsquo;s edge; then
woke up in the hospital wing; then went back in time; &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt;
suggested to Hermione that they burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin and grab
the rat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, these events all occur, and they occur &lt;em&gt;in this order&lt;/em&gt; for
Harry and Hermione.  It&amp;rsquo;s because they occur in this order that when
Harry suggests to Hermione that they burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin, it&amp;rsquo;s
too late.  They &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; left the cabin with Scabbers, and nobody
burst in.  That event occurred long before Harry suggests they burst
into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin, and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing they can do about it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Is the future fixed as well?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordering events in terms of personal time is no less accurate than
ordering them in terms of external time.  But when we think through
what this means, we&amp;rsquo;ll notice a surprising consequence: if time travel
is possible, then the future is just as fixed as the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s think about Harry&amp;rsquo;s fight with the Dementors at the lake&amp;rsquo;s edge.
Harry, about to collapse, sees his Patronus running across the lake,
back to his future self.  Just because he doesn&amp;rsquo;t recognize himself
doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it&amp;rsquo;s any less true that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt; on the other side of
the lake.  But this means that at some point in his personal-time
future, Harry will &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; be at that spot to cast the Patronus
Charm.  His future actions must and &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; eventually lead him to that
spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry, on the verge of collapse at the edge of the lake, has certain
things he is &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; to do in his personal future, because Harry,
standing on the the other side of the lake, is &lt;em&gt;doing those things&lt;/em&gt; at
the very same external time.  But does this mean that the future is
&lt;em&gt;just as fixed&lt;/em&gt; as the past?  All we&amp;rsquo;ve established so far is that
there are things that Harry has to do at &lt;em&gt;some point&lt;/em&gt; in his personal
future.  But isn&amp;rsquo;t there some flexibility about when he gets around to
doing them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, no.  We&amp;rsquo;ve agreed that when Harry finally faints at the
edge of the lake, he&amp;rsquo;s already (in terms of external time) cast the
Patronus.  That means that he&amp;rsquo;s also already done all the individual
actions that brought him to the spot where he cast the Patronus.  He&amp;rsquo;s
already hid in the forest, watching Snape pick up his Invisibility
Cloak; he&amp;rsquo;s already rescued Buckbeak; he&amp;rsquo;s already suggested to
Hermione that they burst into Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s cabin; and he&amp;rsquo;s already
appeared in the Entrance Hall after traveling back in time with
Hermione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when he appeared in the Entrance Hall, he was three hours older
than the Harry he hears walking down to Hagrid&amp;rsquo;s with Ron and
Hermione.  (If another witch or wizard measured his physical age at
that point, they could compare that with the time of his birth and
&lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that he&amp;rsquo;s a time traveler from three hours in the future.)  So
when Harry faints at the lake&amp;rsquo;s edge, it&amp;rsquo;s already determined that
very soon, he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; go back in time three hours and perform all those
actions that he&amp;rsquo;s already performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can actually be even more precise than &amp;ldquo;very soon&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;Hermione
checks her watch just after Harry casts the Patronus and sees that in
45 minutes, Dumbledore will leave the hospital wing, which is when
they go back in time.  So when Harry faints, it&amp;rsquo;s already determined
that in 45 minutes, he&amp;rsquo;s going back in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all a bit mind-bending, but the upshot is that &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; time
travel is possible, then our futures seem to be determined.  &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of
our futures, not just the futures of time-travelers: since Harry&amp;rsquo;s
future includes his casting the Patronus Charm from across the lake,
nobody else can &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; do anything that would prevent him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem alarming and implausible, but think about it: how
could Professor Trelawney make &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; correct predictions otherwise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Postscript: Pottermore? How about Potter&lt;em&gt;less!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pottermore.com&#34;&gt;Pottermore&lt;/a&gt; entry for
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pottermore.wikia.com/wiki/Time-Turner&#34; title=&#34;Pottermore Wikia&#34;&gt;Time-Turners&lt;/a&gt; includes this alarming statement from Department
of Mysteries employee Saul Croaker:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All attempts to travel back further than a few hours have resulted
in catastrophic harm to the witch or wizard involved. It was not
realised for many years why time travellers over great distances
never survived their journeys. All such experiments have been
abandoned since 1899, when Eloise Mintumble became trapped, for a
period of five days, in the year 1402. Now we understand that her
body had aged five centuries in its return to the present and,
irreparably damaged, she died in St Mungo&amp;rsquo;s Hospital for Magical
Maladies and Injuries shortly after we managed to retrieve her. What
is more, her five days in the distant past caused great disturbance
to the life paths of all those she met, changing the course of their
lives so dramatically that no fewer than twenty-five of their
descendants vanished in the present, having been &amp;ldquo;un-born.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;rsquo;ve seen, this is impossible.  The notion of time-travel that
exists in the popular imagination and in films like &lt;em&gt;Back to the
Future,&lt;/em&gt; where Marty McFly sees his childhood photos begin to fade
when he threatens to prevent his parents from meeting, are
nonsensical.  We must therefore conclude that the above statement from
Professor Croaker is in error.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>